School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Art Professions, Department of Art and Art Professions Dissertations 1940-1995 RG 26.0
New York University Archives
Records of the School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Art Professions (SEHNAP), Department of Art and Art Professions Dissertations
1940-1995
RG 26.0
New York University Archives
9.0 linear feet 9 linear feet
Dissertations and theses for the Art Department of the School of Education. The thesis topics vary widely in subject and time period.
Arrangement
The theses remain in their original order.
The files are grouped into one series.
Scope and Content Note
In the 1940's, PhD candidates in the department of Art Education spent at least one year working on what was then referred to as a thesis. By the 1990's, students in Art and Arts Professions produced dissertations as part of their PhD requirements. This collection contains dissertations and theses on a broad range of topics pertaining to art history, education and theory across diverse geographical and historical categories. Many of the theses/dissertations are bound, and some are in multiple volumes.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Department of Art and Art Professions is part of the New York University School of Education, which is currently called the Steinhardt School of Culture, Education, and Human Development. The School was founded in 1890 as the School of Pedagogy, renamed the School of Education in 1921, and was called the School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Professions (SEHNAP) from 1974 to 1994.
At the beginning of the period represented by this collection, the School of Education's Art courses were taught within Art Education, a program that focused on the training of teachers, supervisors, and directors of art education in elementary and secondary schools. By the 1990's, the renamed Department of Art and Art Professions had expanded to offer majors in Studio Art, Arts Education, Art Therapy, and Arts Administration, offering a PhD in Arts and Humanities or Art Education. The current focus of the program is interdisciplinary, providing theoretical and historical training in visual culture to support art administrators, educators, and scholars.
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Please contact the Archives with specific questions regarding access to such records.
This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The Art and Arts Professions dissertations were transferred to the New York University Archives by the Department of Art and Arts Professions in 1997.
Acconci, Vito, 1940-; Anderson, Walter Inglis, 1903-1965; Bochner, Mel, 1940-; Demuth, Charles, 1883-1935; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994; Hesse, Eva, 1936-1970; New York University. Dept. of Art and Art Professions.; New York University. School of Education, Health, Nursing, and Arts Professions.; Veblen, Thorstein, 1857-1929; Art |x Study and teaching.; Art |z Nigeria.; Artists |z Thailand.; Dissertations.; Failaka Island (Kuwait).; Gravure.; Industrial design.; Jaina art.; Jones Beach State Park (N.Y.); K.K. Kunsthistorisches Hofmuseum |z Vienna |z Austria.; Paris (France) |x History.; Romanticism |z England.; theses.
- Series I
  - Untitled Dissertation on Thai Art, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227125 7
  - A Study of the Works of Twelve Modern Thai Painters, Jamuni, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Modern Thai Painting: A Study of Twelve Thai Painters in the Context of Thai Tradition and Changing Art Education, Jamuni, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Tripartite Description of Jaina-Style Figurines, Kellers. Vol. 2 - Illustrations, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A Tripartite Description of Jaina-Style Figurines, Kellers. Vol. 3 - Computer Printouts, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Tripartite Description of Jaina-Style Figurines, Kellers. Vol. 1 - Text and Bibliography, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Influence of Romanticism on British Painting of the Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries, Smith, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - A Hermeneutic Study of Selected Paintings of Women Religious Artists of the 12th and 20th Centuries, by Therese McGuire. Vol. 1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227126 5
  - From Socrates to Thomas, by R.F. Shubart. Vol. 1, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - An Analysis of the Concept of the Artist's Intention in the Visual Arts, by Gertrude Kessel, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Guidelines for a Course on Women Artists, Arnold, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clement Greenberg: His Critical and Personal Relationships with Jackson Pollock and Selected Post Painterly Abstractionists, by Janet Jones, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Papermaking from Selected Malaysian Fibers: An Investigation of its Artistic Potential Through Creation of Paper Artworks, by Chew Teng Beng, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Malcah Zeldis: Her Life and Evolution of her Work, by Henry Niemann, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227127 3
  - The Art of Windsor Chairmaker: An Aesthetic Inquiry, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - An Abstract of Ways of Meaning in Selected Contemporary Sculpture Manifesting Hard and Soft Form Characteristics, by Carl Rattner, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - An Abstract Toward the Development of a Critically Responsive Audience: An Aesthetic Inquiry Employing Edward Bullough's Theory and Criticism of Contemporary Theatre, by Nina M. Wasserman, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Design Dilemma: A Study of the New Morality of Industrial Design in Western Societies, by Marcia M.O. Sampaio Rosefelt, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Design Dilemma: A Study of the New Morality of Industrial Design in Western Societies, by Marcia M.O. Sampaio Rosefelt, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Development of a Model for the Operation of a University Art Gallery, by Gene Ellis Sills, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227128 1
  - Integrating the Arts in Public Education: The Symbolization Process as Wholistic Experience, by Jerrilee Cain, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A Phenomenological Approach to Aesthetic Education in the Secondary School Painting Class, by Barry Paul Lieberman, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Symbolic Meaning of the Cross in Contemporary American Painting. A Comparative Study of Statements by Selected Artists and Critics, by Walter Gaudnek, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - An Abstract of The Art of Eva Hesse, Mel Bochner, and Vito Acconci as Indicative of Shifts in Mainstream Art Between 1966 and 1973, by Martha Smith-Allen, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Proposal for the Re-Certification of the New York University Art Education Programs, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - A Study of the Development of An Artist: Charles Demuth, by A. Eisman, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227129 9
  - Paris: The City of Light, by Dale McConathy, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Paris: The Culture Industry - A Guide, by Dale McConathy, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Paris: Between the Wars by by Dale McConathy, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sacred Space: An Aesthetic for the Liturgical Environment, by Dennis McNally, SJ, 19682 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Five Plays: A Repetory of Children's Theatre to be Performed by and for Children, by Lowell S. Swortzell, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sacred Space: An Aesthetic for the Liturgical Environment, by Dennis McNally, SJ, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Mitchell - Projected Color Images as Stimuli for Gravure I, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mitchell - Projected Color Images as Stimuli for Gravure II, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Hug - The Origin and Development of the Teacher Education Unit at New York University, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Randall - The Progress of Transformation in Contemporary Assemblage copy 2, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Ceramics of Failaka: A Question of the Function of Tradition in Artistic Creation, by Safwat Nourel-Din, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Role of the Visual Arts in Post-Modern and Late-Modern Architecture: A Comparative Study. Final Dissertation Copy. Robert J. Daniel, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227130 7
  - Integrated Art Education, by M. Colleen Harrigan, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Development of Case Studies and Conceptual Analyses of Effects of Art Therapy with Emotionally Disturbed and Brain-Injured Adolescents, by Erika Steinberger, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Puerto Rican Art in New York: Painters and Their Work, by Patricia Wilson, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Kunsthistorisches Museum in Vienna, by Evelyn Samuel, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - The Relationship Between the Crafts and the Fine Arts in the United States from 1876 to 1980, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Validity in Biblical Interpretation, by F. Eugene Guest, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - A Creative Process Produces an Autobiographical Novel: An Aesthetic Historical Study, by Carl A. Winderl, jr. vol. I, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227131 5
  - A Creative Process Produces an Autobiographical Novel: An Aesthetic Historical Study, by Carl A. Winderl, jr. vol. II, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - A Creative Process Produces an Autobiographical Novel: An Aesthetic Historical Study, by Carl A. Winderl, jr. vol. III, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - A Creative Process Produces an Autobiographical Novel: An Aesthetic Historical Study, by Carl A. Winderl, jr. vol. IV, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - A Study of the Origins, Development, and Significance of Southern Nigerian Traditional Pottery, Moses Oladipo Fowowe, vol. I, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - A Study of the Origins, Development, and Significance of Southern Nigerian Traditional Pottery, Moses Oladipo Fowowe, vol. II, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Untitled Dissertation (Embroidery in Jordan) by Insaf Frain, 0000 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Ornstein: A Guide to Creative Art and Science Experiences in the Third and Fourth Grades of the Elementary School II, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227132 3
  - Ornstein: Intesifying Learning Through Creative Experiences in Art and Science in the Third and Fourth Grades of the Elementary School I, 0000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Arts and Crafts as Factors in Social Adjustment With Special Reference to Juvenile Deliquency, Benjamin Katz, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to the Study of Contemporary Civilization: A Textbook and Study Guide, Katharine Augusta Sutton, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Sparrow: The Choreographic Devices: Their Nature and Function as Related to the Principle of Opposition, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation The Environmental Design of Jones Beach State Park: Aesthetic and Ecological Aspects of the Park's Architecture and Landscape, by R. Marc Fasanelle, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Natural Forms: The Horn Island Logs and Watercolors of Walter Inglis Anderson (1903-1965), Cynthia Elyce Rubin, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Kolodny - An Interpretative Study of the Social, Political, Economic and Educational Views of Thorstein Veblen, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    bar code #: 3 1142 04227133 1
  - Boyum - The Grapes the Lilac Grows, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Gall - Creative Work for Children Talented in Art, 1932 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Crawford - Counseling with Teachers Concerning Visual Education, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Tobin - Art Experiences for the Maladjusted Adolescent, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mitchell - Projected Color Images as Stimuli for Gravure IV, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell - Projected Color Images as Stimuli for Gravure III, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 7)